Guide to the Zoroastrian Association of Houston oral history interviews and ephemera, 2014-2016 MS 624
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas
Zoroastrian Association of Houston oral history interviews and ephemera
2014-2016
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas https://library.rice.edu/woodson
Zoroastrian Association of Houston
MS 624
0.25 Linear Feet (1 box and online digital content)
This is a collection of oral history interviews of members of the Zoroastrian Association of Houston (ZAH), conducted by fellow members of the ZAH.
Biographical/Historical note
The Zoroastrian Association of Houston (ZAH) was established in 1977 to preserve Zoroastrian religious practices and rich and varied culture. Members gather at the Zarathushti Heritage & Cultural Center, built in 1998, to learn, celebrate, and worship together. Sunday school classes and many other interest groups meet on a monthly basis. Conferences, lectures, workshops, intercultural events, plays, dance programs, art exhibits, interfaith activities as well as observances and celebrations are held at the Center. The ZAH is an active member of the Federation of Zoroastrian Associations of North America (FEZANA). In 2000, over two thousand Zoroastrians gathered in Houston from all over to world to attend the Seventh World Zoroastrian Congress - the first World Congress to be held outside India or Iran. The World Zarathushti Chamber of Commerce was launched in Houston. The FEZANA Information Research & Education Systems (FIRES), a centralized collection of Zarathushti books, manuscripts, literature, and magazines, is located at the ZAH library.
Scope and Contents note
Oral history interviews of the Zoroastrian Association of Houston members, conducted in Houston, Texas, in 2014-2016. Formats include interview transcripts, photographs and streaming audio, as well consent forms signed by the interviewees allowing online sharing of these materials.
Conditions Governing Access
This material is open for research. Please see transcripts, photographs and audio online at https://scholarship.rice.edu/handle/1911/77529.
Stored offsite at the Library Service Center and require 24-hour notice for retrieval. Please contact the Woodson Research Center at 713-348-2586 or woodson@rice.edu for more information.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
This material was donated by the Zoroastrian Association of Houston in 2014 and 2016.
Related Materials
Additional interviews of members of the Zoroastrian community in Houston are also available online, as part of the Houston Asian American Archive oral histories. See https://scholarship.rice.edu/handle/1911/79695" >https://scholarship.rice.edu/handle/1911/79695
Accruals note
Additions to this collection may be expected over time.
Index Terms
Subjects
Social life and customs; Asian Americans; Zoroastrianism; Churches; Education
Document Types
digital audio formats; transcripts; Oral histories; invitations
- Series I: Oral history interviews and audio files, Zoroastrian Community Center, 2014, 211147
  - Mehelli D. Behrana oral history interview (wrc05178), 05/03/2014; 211192 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Scope and Contents
    Transcript, photographs, and interview consent form.
  - Jerbanoo P. Bhadha oral history (wrc05179), 05/03/2014; 211187 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Peshotan Bhadha oral history (wrc05180), 05/03/2014; 211182 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Meherwan Phiroz Boyce oral history (wrc05181), 05/03/2014; 211177 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Nano Daroowala oral history interview (wrc05182), 05/03/2014; 211173 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Ardeshir (Adi) Rustomji Desai oral history (wrc05183), 05/03/2014; 211168 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Homi Erani oral history interview (wrc05184), 05/03/2014; 211162 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Transcript, photographs, interview consent form, and additional documents from Erani.
  - Katie Irani oral history interview (wrc05186), 05/03/2014; 211152 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Pilloo Ilavia oral history interview (wrc05185), 05/03/2014; 211157 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Hoshang Tehmurasp Sethna oral history (wrc05138), 211148 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    Photographs and interview consent form. No transcript currently available.
- Series II: Oral history interviews and files, Zoroastrian Community Center, 2016
  - Behram Billimoria oral history interview, August 24, 2016 (wrc08017) (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Rohinton Deputy oral history interview, August 26, 2016 (wrc08018) (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Vehishta Kaikobad oral history interview, August 24, 2016 (wrc08019) (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Shaheen Rustom oral history interview, March 20, 2016 (wrc08020) (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Series III: Ephemera
  - Navjote ceremony invitations and letters, 2003-2014 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Zoroastrian wedding invitation, 2012 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Zoroastrian Association of Houston Directory, 2014 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Series IV: Oral history interviews, 2020-2021
  - Sam Badha oral history interview, 2020-09-21
  - Bahadur Sarkari oral history interview, 2020-11-11
  - Farokh Billimoria oral history interview, 2020-12-11
  - Jamshed Elavia oral history interview, 2021-01-05
  - Jal Guzder oral history interview, 2020-10-21
  - Cyrus Bharucha oral history interview, 2020-10-08